Viral hepatitis is inflammation of the liver parenchyma.
It's usually due to hepatitis virus,
but it's important to note that other causes include EBV and CMV.
Recall from our discussion of infectious mononucleosis,
which was caused by EBV or CMV,
that you could also get a hepatitis, and I discussed that there.
Now our discussion here will focus on hepatitis virus,
and this can cause an acute hepatitis,
which may progress to chronic hepatitis.
Patients with acute hepatitis present with jaundice,
and this is due to a mixed conjugated bilirubinemia
and an unconjugated bilirubinemia.
Now the conjugated bilirubinemia is due to the fact that you destroy bile ductuals,
and so some of the conjugated bilirubin leaks out.
And the unconjugated bilirubinemia is due to the fact that you destroy hepatocytes,
and so you decrease the conjugating ability of the liver.
Now these patients will also have dark urine,
and the reason they have dark urine is because the conjugated bilirubin
is water-soluble and will be filtered by the kidney into the urine.
The patients can also have fever, malaise, and nausea,
and these are some of the signs of the fact that they've got inflammation within the liver.
On laboratories, there will be elevated liver enzymes.
Classically, the ALT will be greater than the AST,
and the symptoms of acute hepatitis usually last less than six months.
And that's important because the presence of symptoms
and appropriate serologic markers for greater than six months
would equal chronic hepatitis, as we'll discuss in a moment.
When you have acute hepatitis, you get inflammation within two areas.
There's inflammation within the portal tracts,
and also inflammation between the hepatocytes within the lobules of the liver.
This image here highlights inflammation between the hepatocytes,
and you can see all of these hepatocytes here,
and then you can clearly see the inflammatory infiltrate in between the hepatocytes.
Now, recall that if the hepatocytes are infected with virus,
they're then going to present abnormal proteins on their MHC class 1.
That MHC class 1 will be recognized by CD8-positive T cells,
and so the hepatocytes will undergo cytotoxic killing.
Of course, that would result in apoptosis of the hepatocytes,
and that's the mechanism of the destruction of the hepatocytes in acute hepatitis.
Chronic hepatitis is defined as the presence of symptoms in appropriate serology
that lasts for greater than six months.
Of course, chronic hepatitis has a risk of progression to cirrhosis,
and we'll hear more about that when we discuss cirrhosis.
Important to note that in chronic hepatitis,
the inflammation predominantly involves the portal tracts,
and so here I'm outlining a portal tract,
and you can see that within the lobule of the liver here and here,
we don't really see much inflammation,
but clearly within the portal tract,
you can see all these small blue dots representing inflammatory cells.
There are multiple hepatitis viruses that can cause hepatitis.
The first two that we'll talk about are hepatitis A and hepatitis E.
These have a fecal-oral transmission.
Hepatitis A is classically acquired by travelers,
and hepatitis E is classically acquired from contaminated water or undercooked seafood.
Now, the reason why I bunch these two together
is because they both produce acute hepatitis with no chronic state.
The presence of IgM marks active infection,
and the presence of IgG indicates that the patient has resolved the infection
or has been immunized.
Now, remember that immunization is only available for hepatitis A virus.
Very high yield to note that hepatitis E infection in a pregnant woman
is associated with fulminant hepatitis,
where the patients get liver failure with massive liver necrosis,
and this is particularly high yield to note.
Again, hepatitis E in a pregnant woman is highly worrisome.
Hepatitis B virus is transmitted parentally,
which basically means that it is transmitted via piercing of the skin or the mucous membranes.
So this can occur during childbirth, during unprotected intercourse,
or during IV drug abuse.
Hepatitis B classically results in acute hepatitis
and only rarely progresses to chronic disease.
Only 20% of cases will actually go on to result in chronic disease.
When a patient has a hepatitis B infection, they can present in varying stages.
For example, the acute phase or the resolved phase, etc.
And serology is particularly useful for subclassifying these different stages.
And so we've got to spend a little bit of time on this chart,
and it's particularly high yield.
Now, the way by which I'm going to do this is to just introduce to you
some very simple principles,
and hopefully those principles will take you a long way.
The first principle is that hepatitis B's surface antigen
is the key marker of infection.
First of all, it is the first serologic marker to rise during the acute phase.
When the patient resolves the acute phase and resolves the infection, it disappears.
And if it is present for greater than six months,
then that defines the chronic state.
Principle number two,
the key marker of acute battle is IgM against the core.
And the way I think about this is that the core is the core of the matter,
at least serologically.
And so, here you have hepatitis B core antibody,
and you can see that during the acute battle for the first six months,
it is the major antibody that you use to try to defeat the virus.
Now, what happens during the acute phase is you produce the IgM,
and it hammers away, hammers away, hammers away at the virus,
until it eventually knocks out the virus,
creating something called the window phase.
The only thing that will be positive during the window phase will be IgM.
And then, towards the end of that battle, IgG will be produced.
If you have permanently destroyed the surface antigen and other markers of the virus,
then you'll call that a resolved infection.
However, again, if surface antigen is present for greater than six months,
then that would indicate that the patient now has chronic disease.
Principle number three is that the sign of victory is the presence of IgG against the surface.
And so, here you have hepatitis B surface antibody.
You get IgG only if the infection resolves.
And if you go into the chronic state, you will not develop IgG against the surface.
And so, again, the presence of IgG versus the surface indicates that you have won the battle.
Now, there is one other way to win the battle, and that would be to give immunization.
Remember that in immunization, we simply give the surface antigen to the patient with nothing else,
and they'll produce an IgG against the surface antigen,
and then will be protected against the virus.
One other principle to note is that whenever you have IgG against the surface,
it also protects you, as is clearly illustrated by the notion of the immunization.
Now, the final point, and the final high-yield point,
is that the envelope antigen indicates infectivity.
So, here's the envelope antigen, and it's present during the acute phase.
It may be present during the chronic phase.
But whenever it's present, it indicates that the virus can be transmitted to another person.
Now, that's not hard to remember, because if you mail a letter to a friend, you need an envelope.
And if the virus needs to go to another person, it's going to need the envelope antigen.
So, that's the way I remember that.
Now, moving along to hepatitis C virus, this is also transmitted parentally,
which basically means that it occurs through a nick in the skin or the mucous membranes.
And, of course, that could occur with IV drug abuse, unprotected intercourse, or needle sticks.
The risk from transfusion of blood products is almost non-existent,
and that's because we screen the blood supply.
Hepatitis C will result in acute hepatitis, but it often progresses to chronic disease.
The key serology is hepatitis C virus RNA.
The presence of RNA confirms infection during the recovery.
The RNA levels will go down, and the persistence of RNA indicates chronic disease.
Now, the final discussion here is the hepatitis D virus.
The only thing you have to know here is that hepatitis D cannot infect by itself.
It requires hepatitis B for infection.
And there are two possible ways by which this can occur.
The first is that a patient has a pre-existing hepatitis B virus infection,
and then they subsequently get hepatitis D on top of that prior B.
That is called superinfection.
The second possibility is that the patient gets hepatitis B and hepatitis D together at the same time.
That's called co-infection.
What you have to know, especially for board examinations,
is that superinfection upon a pre-existing hepatitis B virus
is more severe than co-infection with B and D at the same time.
And that's the last point from this particular table.